Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
本系列基于并受 希里·玛塔吉·尼玛拉·德维的教导所启发，
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
旨在探索两个相互关联的领域之间 的演化关系，
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
这两个领域在粗糙和精微的层面 表达了人类的知觉。
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
它致力于阐明当前科学 对人类神经解剖学的理解，
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
特别是对自主神经系统的理解，
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
与瑜伽传统文献中所描述的 所谓“精微系统”之间的关系。
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
最终，本系列试图带领观众 踏上这段探索之旅，
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
透过希里·玛塔吉·尼玛拉·德维所教的冥想法， 来体验这些关系。
Thanks to all our viewers for joining us in this series.
感谢所有观众参与本系列节目。
We are on this exploration into the fascinating intersection
我们正踏上这趟探索之旅， 探讨引人入胜的交集点，
of neuroscience and spirituality with Dr. Ashish Pradhan,
即神经科学与灵性， 与我们同行的有阿希什·普拉丹医生，
who is a distinguished leader in neurology and cardiovascular medicine. Welcome, Dr. Ashish.
他是神经学与心血管医学领域的杰出领导者。 欢迎，阿希什医生。
Thank you, Monikaji.
谢谢您，莫妮卡吉。
Great to be back again.
很高兴再次来到这里。
Definitely.
当然。
My pleasure.
我的荣幸。
The question that I always ask you
当我们谈论每一个能量中心，
about every energy center that we talk about,
我总会问您一个问题，
I know today we are focused on the fifth energy center.
我知道今天我们专注于 第五个能量中心。
So, what is the relationship between
那么自主神经系统
the autonomic nervous system and the fifth energy center?
与第五个能量中心之间有什么关系？
And then what organs does this center relate to in human anatomy?
还有，在人体解剖学中， 这个中心与哪些器官相关？
We also hear about the thyroid gland, maybe a little bit about that.
我们也听说过甲状腺， 或许可以稍微谈谈这个。
Let us begin as always.
让我们像往常一样开始吧。
The fifth energy center, also called the Vishuddhi Chakra,
第五个能量中心，也称为喉轮 (Vishuddhi Chakra)，
has a critical role to play in human evolution.
在人类演化中扮演着 至关重要的角色。
Each of these centers do, we have been saying from the very beginning, the whole system is integrated.
每个能量中心都是如此， 我们一开始就说，整个系统是整合的。
It is not unitary.
它不是单一独立的。
But this energy center is kind of special in its own way.
但这个能量中心有其独特之处。
It has 16 aspects to it according to the Sahaj teachings.
根据霎哈嘉的教导， 它有十六个面向（瓣）。
So if we look at human evolution from the time again,
因此，如果我们再次回顾人类演化，
from when it started, unicellular life forms
从单细胞生命形式开始，
right up to the vertebrate animals or mammals such as us,
一直到像我们这样的 脊椎动物或哺乳动物，
this energy center is believed to have played two roles.
这个能量中心被认为扮演了 两个角色。
One is that this energy center controls the voice box or the larynx.
一是这个能量中心控制着 喉头或喉部。
It also controls the movement of our arms and so on and so forth.
它也控制我们手臂的运动等等。
But it is a speech that I would like to focus on a little bit.
但我想稍微聚焦在语言方面。
So, as we’ve said several times in this series,
正如我们在本系列中多次提到的，
we have the autonomic nervous system within us—
我们体内有自主神经系统——
which is what this series is about.
这也是本系列的重点。
Two components: sympathetic, parasympathetic.
它有两个部分： 交感神经和副交感神经。
And the larynx or the voice box is controlled by two nerves
喉头或喉部由两条神经控制，
called the recurrent laryngeal nerves and they are offshoots.
称为喉返神经 (recurrent laryngeal nerves)，它们是分支。
They come from the vagus nerve and the vagus nerve comes from the midbrain.
它们来自迷走神经， 而迷走神经来自中脑。
So the long and short of it is this, that in evolution,
长话短说，在演化中，
one of the reasons according to evolutionary biologists,
根据演化生物学家的说法，
one reason the Homo sapiens enjoys a pre-eminent position
智人（Homo sapiens）享有 卓越地位的原因之一，
on this planet is its ability to communicate.
就是其沟通能力。
So communication is one of the key functions
所以沟通是这个能量中心所促成的
enabled by this energy center.
关键功能之一。
And if you think about it, it is the power of speech.
如果你仔细想想， 这就是语言的力量。
Now, it is not that sounds that are produced by an organism
这并不是说由生物产生的声音
are unique to the Homo sapiens.
是智人所独有。
There are multiple other species,
有许多其他物种，
thousands and thousands of them that produce sound.
成千上万的物种会发出声音。
Birds produce sounds, animals produce sounds, mammals such as whales and dolphins in the water,
鸟类会发声，动物会发声， 水中的哺乳动物如鲸鱼和海豚
they produce sounds.
也会发声。
So producing sound by itself is not the issue.
所以发出声音本身 不是问题所在。
In all these organisms, this energy center probably played a role.
在所有这些生物体中，这个能量中心 可能都扮演了某种角色。
But in the human being, it is the most evolved
但在人类身上，它是最为进化的，
because it allows us to form what we call speech patterns
因为它让我们能够形成 我们称之为“语言模式”的东西，
that we call words and therefore language.
即我们所说的词语，进而形成语言。
And it is this language that has allowed, or the ability to create languages,
正是这种语言，或创造语言的能力，
to speak languages, to communicate with each other in languages,
说语言、用语言相互沟通的能力，
which unfortunately sometimes also leads to divisions
不幸的是，有时也会导致
amongst individuals and communities and nations.
在个人、社群 和国家之间的分裂。
But it is this power of language that has enabled us
但正是这种语言的力量， 使我们能够
to gain dominance over other species.
在其他物种中占据主导地位。
Now, how did that pan out?
那么这是如何实现的？
How did it provide us with an evolutionary advantage?
它如何为我们提供演化上的优势？
So it is hypothesized and there is maybe a full rational background
有一种假说，或许也有 充分的理性背景
as to how this was probably possible,
来解释这可能是如何发生的，
as if we go back to literally millions of years
如果我们回到几百万年前，
and maybe hundreds of thousands of years after that,
以及那之后的数十万年，
when humans started living in caves
当人类开始在洞穴中生活，
with primitive tools,
使用原始工具时，
they were subject to attacks by wild animals.
他们会受到野生动物的攻击。
So let us say two individuals living in the same cave
假设住在同一个洞穴的 两个人，
or near each other could warn each other
或彼此相邻，可以互相警告，
through a pattern of speech that there may be a sabre-toothed tiger close by
透过一种语言模式，告知对方 附近可能有只剑齿虎，
and then banding together, either running away from it
然后他们团结起来， 要么逃离，
or making sure they did not get close to it.
要么确保不靠近它。
That allowed for a survival advantage.
这带来了生存优势。
And then we can expand on this for the next,
我们能就此扩展并讲下去，
as much as we want, but we can see how that ability
但我们可看到那种
to communicate danger, forewarning of a threat
沟通危险、预警威胁的能力——
to an individual or to a family or to a group of individuals,
无论对个人、家庭、一群人 或一个定居点，
to a settlement allowed this to happen.
如何促成了这种生存的优势。
So in human evolution, this center has played a very important role.
所以在人类演化中，这个中心 扮演了非常重要的角色。
The other role that the founder of this system of meditation,
这个静坐系统的创始人， 希里·玛塔吉·尼玛拉·德维女士总是说，
Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi always says,
这个中心的另一个作用是
is that it was this center that allowed us to raise our heads.
它让我们能够抬起头。
So this cervical curvature, if you see the human skeleton
所以这个颈椎曲度， 如果你从侧面看人类骨骼
or the human vertebral column in profile,
或人类脊柱，
you have the cervical curvature, then
你会看到颈椎曲度，
the thoracic curvature and the lumbar
然后是胸椎曲度和腰椎
and the sacral curvatures.
以及荐椎曲度。
So when in the Neanderthal stage or in the Denisovan stage,
所以在尼安德塔人阶段 或丹尼索瓦人阶段，
the other species that preceded the Homo sapiens, if you see the classic biology textbook
在智人之前，这些其他物种， 如果你看经典生物教科书
showing the evolution of people,
中展示的人类演化图，
somebody hunched over and then gradually stood upright.
你会看到一个弯着腰的人， 然后逐渐直立起来。
This upright posture and particularly the raising of the neck
这种直立的姿势， 特别是颈部的抬起，
is believed to have been influenced by this energy center
被认为是受到了 这个能量中心的影响，
through its control of the vertebral column as well as the nerves,
透过它对脊柱以及神经的控制，
both the sympathetic, the parasympathetic
包括交感神经、副交感神经
as well as the skeletal nerves that allow for the musculature
以及让肌肉能 以此方式运作的骨骼神经。
to function in this fashion.
让肌肉能以此方式运作。
Besides the vocal cords, this energy center is responsible for the control of our teeth,
除了声带，这个能量中心 还负责控制我们的牙齿、
our musculature here, our face, the muscles as well as our ears.
我们这里的肌肉、我们的脸、 肌肉以及我们的耳朵。
So again, think about it.
再想想看。
The sense of olfaction, that is a sense of smell.
嗅觉，也就是闻的感觉。
So the sense of smell, the ability to hear and the ability to speak are all functions
所以嗅觉、听觉和说话的能力， 都是由
that are governed by this single energy center.
这一个能量中心所掌管的功能。
And if we go back into our evolutionary process,
如果我们回到我们的演化过程中，
it is believed that the sense of smell was the first
人们相信嗅觉是在所有感官中
amongst all other senses that was evolved or that was developed
第一个演化或发展出来的，
because in the water the little fish had to detect the presence of a predator by smelling
因为在水中，小鱼必须透过 非常原始的嗅觉细胞来侦测
through the very primitive olfactory cells that it had,
捕食者的存在，透过它所拥有的 非常原始的嗅觉细胞去嗅闻，
the presence of a larger animal or a larger being
使之感知较大动物或生物的存在，
because of the chemicals that it emitted through its presence.
这是因为后者所释放出的化学物质。
So the sense of olfaction also gave us that evolutionary advantage as it evolved.
所以嗅觉的演化也给了我们 那种演化上的优势。
The sense of hearing, same thing.
听觉也是一样。
When we heard sounds, the sense of sound, I think we discussed this in a previous episode,
我们在上一集中讨论过， 我们听到声音时——那些听觉细胞，
developed even before the cells that eventually over millions of years became our eyes
经过数百万年， 最终成为我们眼睛的细胞，
or the sense of vision.
因此听觉比视觉更早发展。
So the sense of smell and the sense of hearing allowed us that evolutionary advantage
所以在人类状态演化的过程中， 嗅觉和听觉
as the human condition evolved but
给了我们演化上的优势，
even starting from literally billions of years ago.
但这甚至从几十亿年前就开始了。
So this energy center allowed us to evolve,
所以这个能量中心让我们得以演化，
to gain what we might dare use the word consciousness.
并获得或许我们可以大胆使用 的“意识”。
Who we are as individuals, as a collective,
我们作为个人、作为集体是谁，
as a body started from this particular energy center.
作为一个整体，都始于这个 特定的能量中心。
And that is why this center from a Sahaj point of view
这就是为什么从霎哈嘉的角度来看， 这个中心负责
is responsible for allowing us to have a sense of collectivity
让我们拥有一种集体感，
which we will deal with later in this episode.
我们将在本集稍后讨论这一点。
The thyroid gland, again very, very important,
甲状腺也非常非常重要，
it sits here in front of the trachea in this upper part
它位于气管前方的这个上部位置，
and the thyroid gland secretes hormones
甲状腺分泌了我们都熟悉的荷尔蒙，
that we are all familiar with, that is thyroxine
即甲状腺素
and triiodothyronine, the thyroid T3, T4. Most of us who have undergone exams, know
和三碘甲状腺胺酸，即甲状腺的 T3、T4。 我们大多数做过检查的人都知道
that your internist will ask for the levels of those hormones.
你的内科医生会要求检测 那些荷尔蒙的水平。
Those hormones are very important because they are related
那些荷尔蒙非常重要， 因为它们与
to neural development, the development of the brain.
神经发育，即大脑的发育有关。
So the thyroid hormones help in what is called
甲状腺荷尔蒙有助于所谓的
neurogenesis which means the growth of cells.
“神经新生”(neurogenesis)， 即细胞的生长。
They are important for synaptogenesis which means
它们对“突触新生”（synaptogenesis） 也很重要，
the connectivity between these neurons is very important,
这意味着这些神经元之间的 连结非常重要，
we will deal with this in the final episode.
我们将在最后一集中讨论这个。
But these are synapses through which neurons talk to each other.
但这些是神经元相互沟通的突触。
The presence of these hormones is very important for optimal development of the brain
这些荷尔蒙的存在对大脑的最佳发育 非常重要，
and unfortunately we know that individuals who from birth
不幸的是，我们知道那些从出生就
or lack this hormone do suffer from neurological conditions
缺乏这种荷尔蒙的人，确实会患有 神经系统疾病，
and even sometimes mental retardation.
有时甚至是智力迟缓。
So these hormones are important and that is why
所以这些荷尔蒙很重要，这就是为什么
this energy center, which is the fifth energy center,
这个第五个能量中心，
is so critical for human evolution, for the development of the human brain,
对人类演化、对人脑发育、
the overall development of the nervous system, and the sense of collectivity that we feel
对神经系统的整体发展， 以及我们所感受到的——
both as an individual as part of a larger organism.
作为个体，同时也是更大有机体一部分 的集体感，都如此关键。
I know this answer is very long
我知道这个回答很长，
but there's one interesting hypothesis
但最近有一个有趣的假说被提出，
that has recently been postulated is that this energy center
即这个能量中心
probably also controlled
可能也控制了
the development of the entire skeleton, not just the musculature.
整个骨骼的发展， 而不仅仅是肌肉组织。
But also the bones-muscles essentially sit on the bones,
还有骨骼——肌肉 基本上附着在骨骼上，
the bones provide the framework, the muscles sit on that.
骨骼提供了框架， 肌肉附着其上。
If you have seen images or in museums or sketches
如果你看过图片 或博物馆里的展品或素描，
or what we know from skeletons that have been discovered
或我们从已发现的 远古祖先骨骼中所知，
of our ancestors from the distant past, the lower jaw protrudes forward.
下颚是向前突出的。
So the front part of the face, the upper part of the face
所以脸的前部， 脸的上部在后面，
sits at the back, the lower jaw juts forward.
下颚向前突出。
You see that in apes, in great apes.
你在猿类、大型猿类身上 能看到这一点。
Whereas with the human being, the jaw has gone back
然而在人类身上，下颚已经后缩，
and it is much more level and the reason for that is hypothesized
且变得更平整， 其原因被假设为
to be that this muscle that controls our mastication, the chewing
控制我们咀嚼的肌肉， 也就是咀嚼时
with the lower jaw that goes up and down when we chew food
下颚上下运动， 当我们咀嚼食物时，
which is the lower bone which is called as the mandible bone.
那块下方的骨头 叫做下颌骨。
The mandible bone was much more stronger and protruded forward but through a gene
下颌骨曾经更强壮 且向前突出，但透过一个基因
that controlled for its development is thought
控制其发育，据信这个基因
to have changed the structure of the bone
改变了骨骼的结构，
to the extent that it allowed for the mandible to go back
使得下颌骨得以向后缩，
and because of that the biomechanical forces were reduced
因此生物力学的力量减小了，
or there was less stress on it and that allowed
或者说它承受的压力变小了， 这就让
for the skull to grow.
颅骨得以生长。
Now let's put it all together.
现在我们把这些综合起来。
The lower part of the face which is the mandible, if it was longer it caused more stress here
脸的下部，也就是下颌骨， 如果它更长，会在这里造成更大的压力，
and therefore it pulled this down and did not allow
因此会把它向下拉，不允许
these two parts of the cranium, the skull to expand
颅骨的这两个部分， 即头骨扩张，
and therefore what was inside it, the brain.
也就不允许里面的东西，即大脑扩张。
The brain couldn't expand but because this went back,
大脑无法扩张，但因为这个后缩了，
biomechanical forces reduced here,
这里的生物力学力量减小了，
and that reduced pressure on the cranium bones here
这减轻了这里颅骨在两侧的压力，
on both sides,
从而为里面这团称为大脑的 细胞
to allow for that space for this mass of cells inside called the brain to expand.
提供了扩张的空间。
So it is absolutely fascinating to see, and of course hypothesize, we cannot prove this,
所以看到这一点绝对是引人入胜的， 当然这只是假说，我们无法证明，
there is no way to easily prove this, but it is a fact
没有简单的方法可以证明，但事实是，
that had the mandible been not controlled
如果下颌骨没有被控制
or had it not gone back, maybe the ability
或者没有后缩，也许颅骨
of the cranium to grow and therefore for the brain to expand
生长的能力，以及因此 大脑扩张的能力，
which makes this possible, you and I to speak, would perhaps not have been possible.
也就是让我们你我能够说话的这件事， 或许就不可能发生。
So this energy center is absolutely critical, it's fascinating, it's extremely complex
所以这个能量中心是绝对关键的， 它引人入胜，极其复杂，
but it has probably played a stellar role in human evolution.
但它可能在人类演化中 扮演了卓越的角色。
Definitely.
当然。
It's such a sophisticated mechanism in this evolution.
这演化过程中的机制 真是复杂精妙。
It's so interesting to learn about this.
了解这些真是太有趣了。
So Dr. Ashish, as we understand that every center
阿希什医生，据我们所知， 每个中心
has some qualities that an individual manifests
都有一些个人会展现出来的特质，
and then is there any potential scientific basis
那么，霎哈嘉教导说
to the Sahaj teaching that collective consciousness
集体意识始于这个中心，
begins from this center?
这有任何潜在的科学依据吗？
Yes, it's a little complex mechanism or a complex explanation
是的，这个机制或解释有点复杂，
but we'll try to simplify this.
但我们会试着简化它。
So along with the control of the vocal box, of the larynx,
除了控制喉头、喉部、
of the vocal cords within the larynx
喉内的声带
and the other parts within the face,
以及脸部的其他部分，
this energy center is also believed to control two other plexuses.
这个能量中心也被认为 控制着另外两个神经丛。
One is the cervical plexus and the other one is the brachial plexus
一个是颈神经丛， 另一个是臂神经丛，
and these are again as we have discussed, plexuses are
正如我们讨论过的， 这些神经丛是
groups of nerves, they contain both sympathetic,
一组神经， 它们同时包含交感神经、
parasympathetic and sensory components.
副交感神经和感觉神经的组成部分。
Now the brachial plexus controls the movement of our arms.
臂神经丛控制 我们手臂的运动。
It makes the movement of our arms possible that helps us to communicate.
它使我们手臂的运动成为可能， 这有助于我们沟通。
The interesting fact is that so far as microdissection
有趣的是， 就目前的显微解剖
techniques have allowed us to examine,
技术所能检视的范围，
we do not have parasympathetic nerve endings in the tips of our fingers.
我们的指尖并没有副交感神经末梢。
We only have sympathetic nerve endings
我们只有交感神经末梢，
and although we believe that parasympathetic controls
虽然我们认为副交感神经控制着
everything within the viscera, we have discussed this before
内脏的一切，我们之前讨论过
through the vagus nerve for the most part
主要透过迷走神经，
but there are no sympathetic nerve endings in the tips of our fingers.
但我们的指尖没有 副交感神经末梢。
Now how is that important?
这点为何重要？
It's important from a Sahaj point of view because when
从霎哈嘉的角度来看很重要，
the inner energy rises and it crosses this energy center,
因为当内在能量升起并 穿过这个能量中心时，
the fifth energy center within the central channel,
也就是中脉里的第五个能量中心，
through mechanisms that are physiologically very difficult
透过一些生理学上很难理解的机制，
to appreciate, not yet, I mean human science
目前还不行，我的意思是， 人类科学
has not reached that stage but probably one day will,
尚未达到那个阶段， 但或许有一天会，
however it allows us to feel reality
然而它让我们能够感受到实相，
beyond the cognitive perception.
超越认知感知。
And that is we can feel what are called as vibrations,
也就是说，我们可以感觉到 所谓的“能量振动”，
this cool breeze that does blow through the tips of our fingers.
那股确实流经我们指尖的凉风。
Now let's put it all together.
现在我们把它综合起来。
The energy rises through the central channel which is parasympathetic.
能量透过中脉升起， 中脉是属于副交感神经的。
It is not sympathetic, it is parasympathetic.
它不是交感的，是副交感的。
However the ability to feel the rising of this energy
然而，感受这股能量升起的能力
and the consequence of that rising
以及那升起的后果，
is felt through the tips of our fingers
是透过我们指尖来感觉的，
which is sympathetic.
而指尖是属于交感神经的。
And therefore it is at the level of this energy center
因此，正是在这个能量中心的层面上，
because of these two plexuses, the brachial plexus
因为这两个神经丛， 臂神经丛和颈神经丛，
and the cervical plexus but predominantly the brachial plexus
但主要是臂神经丛，
which innervates our hands and the nerves in our hands,
它支配我们双手和手中的神经，
we can clearly see how this energy center
我们能清楚地看到这个能量中心
allows us to feel these vibrations.
如何让我们感受到这些振动。
Because of Sahaj,
因为在霎哈嘉里，
when this energy rises and you can feel it,
当这股能量升起而你感觉得到它时，
this ability to feel allows you to get this realization
这种感觉的能力让你能领悟到
that you are not just you but you are part of a larger reality.
你不仅仅是你自己， 你是一个更大实相的一部分。
That you exist as part of a larger system, of a larger reality that transcends you.
你作为一个更大的系统、 一个超越你自身的更大实相 的一部分而存在。
And this is the beginning of what is called collective consciousness.
这就是所谓“集体意识”的开端。
So we have individual consciousness: I am breathing,
我们有个人意识：我正在呼吸，
I am seeing you, I am hearing you, you are seeing me,
我看到你，我听到你，你看到我，
so that is our individual consciousness.
这就是我们的个人意识。
But when this inner energy rises, it is only through
但当这股内在能量升起时，唯有透过
the awakening of this energy center
唤醒这个能量中心，才能让我们
that allows us to feel through the sympathetic system
透过交感神经系统去感觉到
what is actually happening within the parasympathetic system.
副交感神经系统内 实际发生的事情。
So let me repeat that.
让我重复一遍。
These nerves at the tips of our fingers do not have parasympathetic endings.
我们指尖的神经没有副交感神经末梢。
So what is otherwise happening within the parasympathetic,
所以在副交感神经系统中发生的事，
we would have no ability to know.
我们本来是无法得知的。
It is only because of this energy center that we can feel
正是因为这个能量中心， 我们才能感觉到
this sensation in our hands - what is happening
这种在我们手中的感觉——
within the parasympathetic nervous system.
感觉到副交感神经系统内发生的事。
And which is why the founder of this system of meditation,
这也就是为何此静坐系统的创始人
Shri Mataji, always used to say that in order to feel
希里·玛塔吉女士总是说 为了感觉到这股凉风，
This cool breeze, what She called vibrations,
也就是她所谓的“振动”，
you need to have this energy center that is in a very good condition,
你需要让这个能量中心 处于非常好的状态，
that is in a healthy condition and therefore it is very important
健康的状态，
to keep this center in a great working condition
确保这个中心处于绝佳的运作状态 是非常重要，
so that you can feel it.
这样你才能感觉到它。
It is a bit complex, but that is how we begin to comprehend
这有点复杂， 但这就是我们如何开始理解
and to experience collective consciousness.
和体验集体意识的方式。
Well, Dr. Ashish, every single discussion with you has been so much interesting.
好的，阿希什医生， 每一次与您的讨论都非常有趣。
We have learnt a lot with you and I do want to once again
我们从您这里学到了很多， 我想再次
thank you for your time today
感谢您今天的时间，
and we look forward to talking to you on the next episode
我们期待在下一集中与您交谈，
about the next energy center.
讨论下一个能量中心。
Thanks once again.
再次感谢您。
And we would encourage our viewers to follow the meditation video that is going to be guided
我们也鼓励观众跟随 接下来将由人指导的静坐影片，
by the founder of this meditation and we wish you all the very best in your experiment
由这种静坐的创始人指导， 我们祝您在您的实验中 以及在霎哈嘉静坐中的体验
and this experience with Sahaj meditation.
一切顺利。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Shri Mataji: Now we come to the other center of Vishuddhi chakra.
希里·玛塔吉：现在我们来到另一个中心， 喉轮。
This is the most important in the sense
就人类生命而言，这是最重要的，
that it ends all your evolution as far as human life is concerned.
因为它终结了你所有的演化。
This has got sixteen petals.
它有十六个瓣。
Outside in the gross it manifests the cervical plexus
在外在的粗糙层面， 它显化为颈神经丛，
and controls your ear, nose, throat, muscles,
并控制你的耳朵、鼻子、喉咙、肌肉，
your eyes and your face.
你的眼睛和你的脸。
Also it controls the first bone and all the bones that go up to the cranial bones.
它也控制着第一块骨头和所有 向上延伸至颅骨的骨骼。
It is the center of your responsibility by which you feel responsibility.
它是你的责任感的中心， 你借此感到责任。
But when this center is awakened, the greater center represents them here,
但当这个中心被唤醒时， 更大的中心在这里代表它们，
because all these centers are represented again in a bigger way in the brain.
因为所有这些中心都在大脑中以 更大的方式再次被代表。
So this center when it is awakened, which is a bigger, larger center of this,
所以当这个中心被唤醒时， 也就是这个中心的更大、更广的中心，
you become collectively conscious.
你会变得有集体意识。
This is the center of collectivity.
这是集体性的中心。
Keep your eyes closed.
请闭上眼睛。
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
首先，请把你的右手 放在你的心脏上。
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
左手一直朝向我。
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
现在，在这里，你必须在你的心中， 带着全然的真诚说： “母亲，我就是那个灵（真我 spirit）吗？”
Ask the question three times in your heart.
在心中问这个问题三次。
This is a very fundamental question.
这是一个非常根本的问题。
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
现在把右手 移到你胃部的左侧，
in the upper part.
在上方的位置。
Here press it.
在这里按压它，
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
现在，这是你的导师中心， 你的指引，你的古鲁 Tattva（导师原则）， 如人们所说。
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
所以问一个问题： “母亲，我是自己的主人吗？”
This is the question to be asked three times.
这个问题要问三次。
Mother, am I my own master?
“母亲，我是自己的导师吗？”
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
现在将你的右手向下移到 腹部的下方。
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
这是完成所有神圣工作的中心，
all the pure work is done.
所有纯粹的工作都从这里完成。
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
所以要问六次， 因为这个中心有六个花瓣：
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
“母亲，请赐予我纯粹的知识。”
Six times you just ask.
就这样问六次。
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
作为这个请求的结果， 昆达里尼（Kundalini）开始被唤醒。
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
现在为了帮助昆达里尼上升， 你必须与祂合作。
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
所以请将你的右手 放在左侧，
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
在你腹部的上部， 然后按在胃上。
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
现在，在这里， 为了帮助昆达里尼上升，
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
你必须充满信心地说： “母亲，我是自己的导师。”
This you have to say ten times.
这句话你要说十次。
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
这就是你要说的十诫，
that Mother, I am my own master.
“母亲，我是自己的导师。”
Now, ten times with full confidence.
现在，充满信心地说十次。
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
现在请把你的右手举到 你的心脏。
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
在这里，你必须说， 再次充满信心地说，
Mother, I am the Spirit.
“母亲，我就是那个灵（真我）。”
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
这是真理，你就是真我。
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
但你必须充满信心地说： “母亲，我是灵。”
This you have to say twelve times.
这句话你要说十二次。
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
现在，人必须知道 全能的上帝是爱的海洋。
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
但最重要的是，祂是宽恕的海洋。
So He forgives.
所以祂会宽恕。
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
无论你做错什么，祂都会宽恕。
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
所以不要感到内疚， 把你的右手
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
放在左侧，在你脖子和肩膀 形成的角落里。
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
现在在这里，你必须 再次充满信心地说十六次：
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
“母亲，我没有罪疚感。”
Please say it, Mother, I am not guilty.
请说出来：“母亲，我没有罪疚感。”
Sixteen times.
十六次。
I am not guilty at all.
我完全没有罪疚感。
Please say it.
请说这句话。
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
现在将你的手放在你的前额上， 这是一个非常重要的中心。
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
在这里，你必须发自内心地说： “母亲，我宽恕每一个人。”
Please say it from your heart.
请发自内心地说。
How many times is not the point.
说多少次不是重点。
Mother, I forgive everyone.
“母亲，我宽恕每一个人。”
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
有些人会说， 宽恕是很困难的。
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
但这是一个迷思， 无论我们宽恕或不宽恕。
We do not do anything in both the cases.
在这两种情况下， 其实我们什么也没做。
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
但如果我们不宽恕， 我们就落入了坏人的圈套。
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
所以请诚心地说： “母亲，我宽恕每一个人。”
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
现在请把你的手放在后脑勺， 也是同一个能量中心，在后脑部位，
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
让你的头靠在手上， 然后稍微向后推。
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
在这里，你必须说， 为了让你自己安心……
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
因为你总是感到内疚， “哦，神圣的力量，如果我做错了任何事，”
please forgive me.
“请宽恕我。”
Please forgive me, from your heart.
请宽恕我。发自你的内心去说。
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
现在请将你的手完全伸直， 把你的手掌中心
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
放在囟门骨区的顶端， 那是你童年时非常柔软的那块骨头。
Press it hard.
请用力按压它。
Press hard your scalp.
用力按压你的头皮。
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
现在你要转动你的手七次， 一边说这句话——这是你必须请求的：
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
“母亲，请赐予我自觉。” 因为我不能强迫你。
So you have to ask for it.
所以你必须请求。
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
转动七次，用力按压， 并非常用力地转动七次。
Slowly saying that.
慢慢地说这句话。